Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 4 -- Letters to Franklin 1779 January-November Mss.B.F85inventory04
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Auer, Deacon M. Ebingen, Würtemberg
    Thanks Dr. Franklin for favor shown to a widow in distress (see August 4, 1779, LIX, 35) and encloses fourfold attest with request to forward same to Germantown.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 8; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Le Ray de
    In reference to dinner at Mme, Helvétiu's house. 2 Notes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Duc, -----
    Has written a eulogium on Franklin's genius. Begs Franklin's influence with his Majesty to annul a certain order; is the victim of calumnious enemies and an envious family.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Gourlade and Moylan. L'Orient
    Requesting his compliance with the annexed letter from Capt. Blackwell of the schooner, "Grand Tiger"; pledge themselves for the faithful performance of any instructions contained in the desired letter of marque.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Alexander, William. St Germain
    Their intention to dine with Franklin the Sunday of the ceremony [Mr. Jonathan Williams's Jr., marriage with his daughter]; expects Franklin and his grandson to dinner on Monday when they may judge of the post-nuptial happiness of the young couple.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1779 September 8; A.L.S. Fra[nci]s Hopkinson. 4p.; The Treasurer of Loans. Philadelphia
    Notification of bills of exchange furnished to the States of New Hampshire, Massachusetts Bay, Rhode Island, Connecticut, New York, New Jersey, Pennsylvania, Delaware, Maryland, Virginia and South Carolina.
  - to [Ferdinand Grand?], 1779 September 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Baumé, -----. Paris
    His efforts to eradicate the spots from the shirt, have failed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Dessoud ?, -----. Loches
    Enclosing a letter which he begs Franklin to forward to Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Delamoignon, Marie Elizabeth. Paris
    Desires news of her nephew, le Chevalier de la Luzerne.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Touzel, W. Tours
    Begs Franklin to procure passage for America, for himself and their friends who desire to join the service.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 11; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Holtzendorff, Louis-Casimir, baron de. Paris
    Requesting Dr. Franklin to appoint a time when he can confer with him on an important matter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Potherye d'Andilly, — vicomte de la. Fort I'Evèque
    In extreme distress on account of debt; throws himself on Franklin's generosity.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 12; A.L.S. 3p.; Torris, John. Dunkirk
    Cheering effect of Franklin's remarks concerning the prisoners and crew of the "Black Prince"; her approaching departure; Mr. Coffyn voices the general desire that her Captain should have a commission. Long delay in the condemnation of the prizes; appeals to Franklin's sense of justice in his misfortunes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 12; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Lee, Arthur. Paris
    Returning journals to Dr. Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779.] September 12; L. 1p.; Jupin, Mlle. Chaillot
    Has just arrived from the country and wishes to see Dr. Franklin. Asks if she can dine with him to-day.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Desire of Mr. Alexander to ascertain from Lord McCartney the particular situation of his estates and affairs on the island [of Grenada].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Raredon, Bartholomew. Fougères
    An American sailor; his various misfortunes since leaving home; his present imprisonment; hopes Franklin will obtain his release.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Emery, Jacob. Montpelier
    His peculiar fitness for the consulship.
    (In French with an English translation.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Holland still vacillating in the affair of the convoys. Congratulates him on the good news from the west.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, Jacques. Paris
    Commissioned by Mr. Cochin to invite Franklin to dine with him at Chatillon and see his garden, which is renowned for its curious and rare plants.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Fournier, Simon-Pierre, la jeune
    Begs Franklin to instruct Lucien Senurier upon certain points connected with the work in hand [the stamping of coin?].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Believes his industry equal to that of any newly-married man; promises Franklin the paper the next day; sends copies of his accounts.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Bridgen, Edward
    Has sent M. Genet samples of metal intended for the current coin; terms on which like coin would be delivered; if a die is needed, that may also be procured.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 17; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Girardot, Haller and Co. Paris
    Enclosing a letter and offering to take charge of any answer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Bett, William. Brest
    Writes on behalf of himself and two other Americans on board the "Gentle Frigate" who are eager to return home; certain that they can be of assistance on board some American vessel.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Morris, Robert. Philadelphia
    The Chevalier de la Luzerne not yet arrived; hopes he may compensate them for the loss of M. [Conrad Alexandre] Gérard [de Rayneval] who enjoyed the esteem of all men, unbiassed by party views. His own opposition to the Constitution of Pennsylvania as well as to parties in Congress, has procured him much unmerited abuse; armed with conscious innocence and unshaken integrity, has never failed to route his enemies.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 18; A.L.S. 4p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    Enclosing copy of a French regulation concerning the formalities to be observed in the condemnation of prizes; advisability of avoiding these difficulties in future by taking French commissions for the "Black Prince" and "Princess"; reasons against such a step; unparalleled success of the "Black Prince" in capturing upwards of thirty vessels in the course of three months; suggests that these two privateers should cruise together in order that the large number of prisoners they will take may be exchanged for Americans in English prisons. The approaching arrival at Dunkirk of the "Black Prince"; desires instructions as to the maintenance of any English prisoners who may be on board.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Greene, Catharine. Warwick
    Family news; poor health of Mrs. Mecom; loves to hear of Franklin's health and of his releasing them from the British yoke.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 20; A.L.S. 7p.; Heimenthal, —, baron de. Valence du Minho
    Wishes to serve in the American army; desires to form artillery corps, to choose his own officers and to have no one placed over him. Encloses anonymous letter of reference which recommends him to Franklin's notice in the highest terms and mentions various other foreign officers whose services would be invaluable to America, especially those in Portugal.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Jacques Rocquette, T.A. Elsevier, and Fréres Rocquette. Rotterdam
    Enclosing a parcel for Franklin, and one for A. Lee to be forwarded to his present address.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 20; A.L. 4p.; Vaughan, Benjamin. London
    Concerning the time of publication of Franklin's works. Sluggish attitude of John Bull. Promises to send further conjectures on the subject of the "Aurora." Crawford's book on "Heat" most admirable. Account of Mr. Henly's having deliberately cut his throat with a pen-knife. Begs for the immediate return of his three manuscripts as he has made no copies.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Vaughan, Benjamin. London
    Begs Franklin to write a letter of recommendation for Langford Lovell and address it to the Governor of Dominica, and at the same time send a duplicate there to Lovell. Desires Franklin to procure him a table or map of Dupont's System of the Economists.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Expects to set out the next day to meet the person and deliver Franklin's letter and instructions.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 22; A.L.S. 2p.; de Samson, -----. Paris
    Implores Franklin's assistance for himself and family.
  - to Franklin's Secretary, 1779 September 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Bertinot, -----. Paris
    Begging Franklin to intercept and return to him a letter addressed by him to M. Gellée, which circumstances have caused him to regret having written.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Conyngham, Ann. Philadelphia
    Entreats his intercession on behalf of her husband, Capt. Conyngham, of the cutter "Revenge," taken prisoner in April and under sentence of death in England. Begs him to forward the enclosed letter as directed, since it may be the means of affording some relief to her poor husband.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Peter Vesey and others. Dunkirk
    A number of sailors, whose time on a French cutter is almost expired, desire Franklin to procure them a passage back to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1779 September 22; A.L.S. 3p.; Nesbitt, Jonathan, & Co.
    Has received information from Philadelphia of the misfortunes of Capt. Conyngham of the "Revenge"; he has been sent to England in irons with the intention of having him tried for piracy; charged with having taken the Harwich packet without having any commission; urges Franklin to prove this accusation false and to do all in his power for the unfortunate man who can expect no mercy at the hands of the English on account of the great harm he has done them.
    Printed in Hale's Franklin in France, I, 344.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1779 September 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Smith, Samuel. Nantes
    Sorry that he was not sufficiently explicit in his former letter, but had destroyed necessary data. Acknowledging receipt of bills of exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Phelps, Charles. Philadelphia
    Writes on behalf of the poor sufferes of Charlestown near Boston; their impoverished and wretched condition; their town pillaged and laid waste by British barbarians; begs Franklin to appeal to the King of France, the nobility and the gentry for aid; cites instances in ancient history of countries helping each other; effect of such broad charities.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., [1779.] September 23; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Bailly, Jean Sylvain. Chaillot
    Inquires if he will be at home to-morrow afternoon. The Comtesse de Beauharnois wishes to pay him a visit. The Chevalier de Cubières, a man of letters, authors of several works in prose and verse, has also desires to pay him a visit.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1779 September 23; A.L.S. 4p.; de Villiequier, Due. Courteille (?)
    Desires instructions for the placing of lightning rods on his town and country house; thinks little of the danger himself but wishes to take all possible precautions on behalf of his family; desires also to be an example to the neighboring proprietors.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Capitaine, -----. Havre
    Requesting Franklin to forward the enclosed letters. Hopes to see him soon at Havre.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 23; A.L.S. 4p.; Torris, John. Dunkirk
    Thinks the judgment and his request to the Admiralty will determine them to sell the prizes. His reasons for soliciting American commissions for his vessels; Irishmen will not fight under French colors. Dissatisfaction expressed by the sailors of the "Black Prince" with the master, Stephen Marchant, and their intention of begging Franklin to replace him by the brave Luke Ryan. Urges Franklin to procure the exchange of the twenty-one prisoners taken from the prizes of the "Black Prince" and to send them to Dunkirk to man the "Black Princess".
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Encloses packets brought by Capt. Bonin from Boston; Captain reports that on account of British reinforcements at Penobscot, the Americans were obliged to destroy their shipping and abandon their attempt. Arrival in Virginia of the "Governor Livingston" and "Mary Fearon"; the "Chasseur" taken and sent to New York.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Bond, Dr Thomas. Philadelphia
    The departure of M. Gérard affords an opportunity of sending messages to Franklin from his friends, Luke Morris, Hugh Roberts and S. Rhoads; speaks of Israel's death being a great loss to the Quakers. The poor-house and hospitals almost untenanted; can scarcely find material for his clinical lectures. Election of Gérard to the American Philosophical Society; presented him with a certificate and a volume of the Transactions emblematically bound. Wrote an essay in defence of inoculation; begs Franklin to give it a friendly reading. News of the Bond family. Hopes now for a more frequent literary correspondence between America and Europe.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    Announcing the arrival of the "Black Prince"; officers report but indifferent success, only two prizes; wishes for Franklin's instructions as to the eighteen prisoners on board.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Flachenfeld, — de. Erlangen
    Begs Franklin to procure him a place in the American army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Martinelli, Vincenzio. Florence
    Sends a copy of his History of England, dedicated to Thomas Walpole, at whose home he met Franklin several times; recommends M. Jean Baptiste la Bordet to Franklin's kind protection.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Raby du Moreau, —. Bordeaux
    Begs for an immediate answer to several questions concerning fighting at Charlestown and the defeat of Prevost.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 26; A.L.S. 1p.; De Freÿ, Capt. Cremona
    Desires that the enclosed letter be forwarded to his brother in America who is Captain in the Count du Pulaski's regiment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Manssallé, -----. Paris
    Asking for an interview in the interest of a merchant of Dunkirk.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Lee, Arthur. Paris
    Congress, while continuing him as their Commissioner to the Court of Spain, has failed to supply him with the necessary funds; if Franklin cannot furnish him with money for his expenses, will return forthwith to America, and deliver up a commission for whose execution the means are not provided.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Priestley, Joseph. Calne
    His successful experiments since the publication of his last volume; vegetation of plants in water; Dr. Fothergill and friends to assist him in defraying the expenses of his next publication.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VI, 423).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Moreau, -----. Paris
    Sends the razors, in order that Franklin may try them before recommending them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Lucy, -----. Meaux
    Begs Franklin's intercession on behalf of several American sailors, now prisoners in France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Marchant, Capt. Stephen. Dunkirk
    Safe arrival in the "Black Prince"; has ten prisoners in Dunkirk jail. Is just setting out for Ostend to take command of the frigate, the "Countess of Berigèn"; will wait on Franklin in a few days with the journal of his entire cruise.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 29; A.L.S. 3p.; Delagrange, -----. Brancourt
    His wife and children suffering for want of food; implores Franklin's assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 29; A.L.S. Rob[ert] Troup, Secretary. 2p.; The Board of Treasury. Philadelphia
    Refers to Resolutions of Congress [of July 26, 1779] that medals to commemorate the storming of Stony Point be struck, and asks that Franklin have them made as soon as possible. Colonel Henry, a gallant actor on the occasion, who bears this letter may be able to assist the medallist.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 29; L.S. 4p.; Brilhac?, ------
    Project to make Concarneau, in Brittany, a free port for the Americans; advantages of the port.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September 29; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Wharton, Samuel. Paris
    Returns the Journals of Congress and the newspapers with thanks; details concerning the price of copper in 1770.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 Sept. 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, Jacques. Paris
    Desiring a letter of introduction for a young Frenchman, M. de Valmer, who expects to travel in America; Madame de Cheminot, one of Franklin's most ardent admirers, seconds this request.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779.; A.N. 1p.; de Jouy, Jaoques Brillon
    Has just arrived from Havre. Called to greet Dr. Franklin and his grandson and to present the compliments of Marquis de la Fayette whom he saw at Havre.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 September --; A.L.S. 4p.; Griffin, Cyrus. Philadelphia
    Enclosing a packet of letters to be delivered to their address. Praises M. [Conrad Alexandre] Gérard [de Rayneval] in the highest terms; the enormous expense of entertaining prevented their paying him all the attention he merited. Reason why Congress thought of recalling all the Commissioners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 October 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Scot, William. L'Orient
    An American subject; served on a French privateer; when he applied for his freedom to go on board an American vessel, he was turned over to a French man-of-war; on refusing to serve he was committed to prison; other American sailors in the same plight; begs Franklin to obtain their release.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 October 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Helker, Jean. Montigny
    Solicits his interest on behalf of a Mrs. Butler, who was taken by the "Black Prince" and lost some bonds and effects.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 October 2; A.L.S. 12p.; James Turing and Son. Middelburg
    Their vessel, "De Brunetta," with a cargo of fruit and wine, was seized as a prize by the American privateer "General Mifflin"; desires indemnity as well as immediate restitution of their property.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 October 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Waiting in this abscure corner for Franklin's friend. Information of the tremedous profits made by Messrs. Fiz[eaux] and G[ran]d on the arms sold to the Americans. Gave one of Mr. Bache's circular letters to Messrs. de Neufville and Sons.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 October 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    The damage inflicted by Paul Jones's squadron; capture of the "Serapis" and "Countess of Scarborough."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 October 4; A.L.S. 7p.; Landais, Capt. Pierre. On board the "Alliance," at Texel
    Transmitting the material parts of his journal of their late cruise, from August 14th to October 3d; their fleet consisted of the "Bon Homme Richard," "Alliance," "Monsieur," "Pallas" and the armed brigs "Vengeance" and "Grandville."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 October 5; A.L.S. 5p; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    Wishes directions in regard to liberating, on security, certain prisoners taken by the "Black Prince." Lists and details concerning prisoners. Intelligence received of the successes of the American Squadron in the German ocean and of the capture of the "Serapis" and "Countess of Scarborough." Hopes Commodore Paul Jones will be able to reach the coast of Norway and repair damages, before the English squadron attacks him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 October 5; A.L.S. 3p.; Greene, William. Warwick, R. I
    Thanking him for his kindness towards his son-in-law and Ray. Prevented from seeing the Chevalier de la Luzerne. Thanks him on behalf of the General Assembly of Rhode Island for the gift of Bennger's History of Geneva, in 6 volumes. Glad to hear of Franklin's grandson being so useful. Franklin's sister has sent him two letters and a dozen cakes of soap and expects to write him again shortly.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 October 6; A.L.S. 4p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Delighted with the news of the capture of the Baltic fleet by Capt. Jones; this good news counteracts the impression of sorrow left by Sir George Collier's expedition. Trusts to Count d'Estaing to revenge their injuries, though not with the cruelty practised by their enemies. His reasons for regretting that he did not rejoin Washington's army; thought he could be of more service on the other side of the Atlantic. Hopes America will soon receive the much-needed supplies of clothes, arms and ammunition. Asks his opinion in regard to aiding the Irish.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 October 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    All the vessels safe in the Road; mentions their names; delivered Franklin's letter to the Commodore [Jones].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 October 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Villiers, Louis-Pierre Dufourny de
    Comte de Chillau, Commander of the frigate "Diligente," desires permission to wait on and relate to him various matters of interest.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 October 7; A.L.S. 2p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Arrival of John Paul Jones, whose orders they have carried out to the best of their ability.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 October 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Schtller, A.C. Brunswick
    Begs him to forward the enclosed letters to his brother, in the Duke of Brunswick's regiment, who was among those surrendered with General Burgoyne.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 31; A.L.S. 7p.; Barry, Amelia. Leghorn
    Her Long and painful residence at Barbary brought to an end. Franklin having been deaf to her repeated supplications in favor of Mr. Barry, has little hope of this letter being honored with any notice. Desires his advice concerning the Proprietary grant for a piece of ground in the Province of Pennsylvania. Annexes a copy of a poem written to James Traile and his lady.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 October 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Capitaine, -----. Havre
    Grateful for the kind things said à propos of the map; begs that serveral copies should be sent to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 October 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Ryan, Luke. Dunkirk
    Expects to have a large cutter completed in four months, with which he hopes to do great damage to the enemy. If his abilities deserve Franklin's protection, begs for a rank in the United States navy; regards American cause as his own.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 October 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Oliver, Thomas. London
    Complains of the terms which the Comte de Durat has laid upon the inhabitants and absentee proprietors of the captured island of Grenada; if the Court of Versailles will not relax the proclamation, their estates must suffer considerably; begs Franklin's interest in the matter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 October 8; A.L.S. 3p.; Vaughan, Benjamin. London
    Asking for letters for Mr. [Thomas] Oliver to the French Governors of Grenada and St. Vincent; may desire letters for his own family in the future; Mr. [William] Manning will request letters only in case of an accident of St. Kitts.